<Document>
# Server Rules
## Rule 0: The Golden Rule - Don't be a dick

This is a 18+ HRP+ whitelisted server. It means, that we are all adults, went through whitelisting and love high quality roleplay. So, let's act like it! Don't be a dick, respect each other and be nice. In-game rivalry and hostility is fine if it is role-played properly and enriches the RP, but out of the game, especially on Discord and in a OOC chat, it is expected, that you are players are nice, helpful and act in a mature way.

If you have an issue with a player, sort it out like adults. Talk in DM or join a voice chat. If you need help with anything, like clarification of rules or if you have any questions, feel free to ask the admins. Our staff is not there to solve your personal feuds and issues, however, we are there to help, if your disagreement is about a rule or something someone did.

## Rule 1: Age Restrictions

In order to play on the Final Frontier server, players must be 18 years old. There are no exceptions. Proof of age can be requested, if there is reasonable doubt about a player's age. While players are not required, to provide such proof, not doing so may result in a server ban.

Players found lying about their age in the whitelist application, will have their whitelist application rejected immediately and will be permanently banned from the Discord and from the server. If whitelist has already been approved, it will be revoked.

Players found being underage at any time, after having their whitelist approved, will be permanently banned from the server and will have their whitelist revoked.

If a player has been permanently banned from the server for lying at their application, they can appeal their ban after becoming 18 years old and after at least six months have passed after a ban has been issued. Ban appeals have to be made on Discord, by opening a ticket. There is no other way and no shortcut to appeal the ban.

## Rule 2: Role-play Expectations

Final Frontier is a High Role Play Plus (HRP+) server. This means, that we expect all our players, to deliver a high quality RP at all time. Low Role Play (LRP) has no place on our server and players, not living up to our high RP standards, will be banned from the server.

As a HRP+ server, we expect our players to act according to their character and in character at all times, acting realistically as they would in their role, as a real person. Local Out of Character Chat (LOOC) is disabled and usage of Out of Character Chat (OOC) is only allowed to clarify bugs, resolve RP issues, or to announce technical issues, such as lag, hardware problems, crashes, having to leave during an RP scene, etc. Whenever possible, instead of OOC Chat, Discord should be used instead.

## Rule 3: Persistence

Unlike vanilla SS14, the Final Frontier server is a persistent gaming environment. Everything carries over from shift to shift, memories, experiences, and reputations are retained and actions, events, emergencies, etc. are remembered. Players can freely talk about these topics and often it may happen, that an event or story arc carries over from shift to shift, lasting several rounds.

Due to the persistent nature of the servers, players are required to act with great care since every action may have potentially serious consequences! If you insult someone, your words won't be magically forgotten after the round ends, and it may take you a long time, to regain that person's trust. If you decide to steal during a shift, your actions will be remembered, even after the shift has ended, possibly barring you from certain jobs or roles.

Space Law will be applied to maintain law and order and punishment is persistent. This means, that if you commit a crime at the end of shift, that crime can and will be investigated at the next shift, and if caught, you might face trial and go to jail. If you commit a crime, punishable by lifetime in prision, your character will permanently move to the brig for the rest of it's existence and if your crime is punishable with execution, your character will permanently vanish.

If your character is seriously wounded or loosing limps, if they undergo surgery or medical treatment or if they suffer from allergies, etc. all those effects will carry over for the duration required to heal. This includes permanent damage, disability and so on. Should your character happen to die, taking damage, beyond revival or cloning or should it be rotting, your character will be gone forever. There is no way, to get it back.

Admin approval is required to void any action or any event. If admin approval is granted, the related event or action will be treated as if it never existed. Should the event include death of or damage to players or loss of property, the original state of the player shall be restored and lost property shall be respawned. If a voided action includes damage or the destruction of ships, stations, or parts thereof, the affected ships or stations should be returned to their original state, prior to the voided action or event.


## Rule 4: Whitelist Requirements and Whitelisting Process

To play on the Final Frontier server, a whitelist is required. This is to ensure, that players meet age and role-play requirements.

Whitelist requirements may be voided during special events or for other reasons. Such voiding or modification of whitelist requirements requires approval of the Project Lead or the Community Manager.

There are two whitelists: Trial Whitelist and Regular Whitelist

Players are required to send a whitelist application on Discord, providing basic information about themselves, such as their age and their username for SS14, as well as information about their role-playing experience and why they want to join the server.

Once a whitelist request has been sent, it has to be reviewed, by an authorized staff member. The reviewing staff member decides, whether the application is complete or not. If the application is incomplete, or there is reasonable doubt about the provided information, the reviewing staff member can investigate further or request additional / missing information.

If a whitelist application is complete and meets the server requirements, it can be accepted by the reviewing staff member and trial whitelist status can be granted. No vouching is required for Trial Whitelist status.

In order to become a regular whitelisted player, it is required to finish basic department or job training, if applicable. Players must be active and engage in role-play with other players. Additionally, player vouching is required, to get full whitelist and for that reason activity and interaction is important during the trial period.

Four vouches are required from other players, to be granted whitelisted status. If the player obtains the required vouches, they get their whitelist, if all above requirements are met.

If there are not enough players around, to receive the necessary votes or if other circumstances make it necessary, staff members can make exceptions or modify the vouch requirements, so that the player has a fair chance, to be accepted.

If a player fails to receive the required vouches for whitelist, their application can be denied or postponed. If the application is postponed, the player must wait at least 15 days, before they can be put up for voting again. This is to allow the player to improve their role-play and interaction, to receive the required vouch.

Players who fail to receive their vouches for being whitelisted a second time, will have their whitelist application denied. If and when they can apply again depends on the staff member, assigned to review the application, and will be communicated to the player in their application.

All players, who got their whitelist approved, are required to create their character bio, before joining the server in an advanced role.

Unless approved otherwise, new players, who desire to join the station crew as professional Nanotrasen personnel (Security, Medical, Cargo, Engineering, etc.), start in the respective trainee or assistant role and undergo basic training. This is to allow them to learn the game and to learn and prove the necessary role-playing skills.

Trial Whitelist players are closely observed by command staff and by their department head and fellow crew members. After basic training has been completed and at least 30 days have passed, active trial whitelist members can talk to their department head, to apply for full whitelist and thus get promoted into a regular job.

Trial whitelist members, who cannot be active for an extended period of time, due to sickness, vacations, military service or other unforeseeable circumstances, should talk to their Department Head or the Head of Personnel, to get their trial whitelist extended. Please note: This should only be done in case of unforeseeable circumstances! If you know, you are going to be away for a prolonged time, please wait with your whitelist application, until you return.

Before putting a trial whitelisted player up for vouching, the department head, the HoP or another authorized command member should talk to the player and let them know, they qualify for full whitelist vouching. They should make sure, the player understands the process, and that they are going to be put up for vouching. Any questions should be answered.

The department head or command members, who puts up a player for regular whitelist vouching, has to make sure, that the player is active and a good fit for the server. They also need to assure, that the player is in good standing, and meets the requirements to be placed on whitelist vouching.

Department Heads, putting a player up for full whitelist, should talk to the HoP, to discuss the case and if the Head of Personnel agrees, the player should be put up for vouch in Discord.

Sufficient time for vouching should be given, to make sure, all players get an opportunity to vouch. For that reason, vouching lasts seven days!

Only members who hold full whitelist status and staff members are eligible to vouch for other players.

While we do not restrict or exclude new players or those who have little to no role-playing experience from joining our server, we expect everybody, to learn and dedicate the required time needed, to play on the server.

Whitelist applicants are strongly encouraged to auto examine themselves to see, whether they got what it takes to play a whitelisted job on our server and if they bring the required dedication. Role-playing can be learned, but playing on a HRP+ server requires a high amount of dedication and time and is not for everyone. If you prefer a more relaxed game-play experience, that is completely fine. There are many LRP and MRP servers around, which you can join.

Whitelist can be removed at any time, if a player fails to meet our RP standards, violates the server rules or participates in any other way of harmful behavior.

Removal of whitelisted status can be for one, several or all roles and can also include a temporary or permanent server ban. Non-Whitelisted players can be banned from the server or specific roles, if they don't meet RP requirements or are otherwise showing that they are not qualified for a particular role.

If a whitelist application has been rejected or a whitelist status has been removed, players can open a ticket on Discord to appeal. Please only do so, if you have a real strong reason to believe, that you have treated wrongly. A senior staff member will review your appeal and make a final decision.

Players being permanently banned from the server, automatically use their whitelist. Should the ban be lifted at a later time, the player can open a ticket and request their whitelist being restored. It is up the staff, to determine, whether full whitelist or trial whitelist is granted.

Permanently banned players are removed from the game through in-game means, by roleplay (transfer to off-sector prison or mental health facility, execution, etc.) - if possible - or removed through admin intervention (character delete), if this is not possible.

It is up to staff, to decide, how to deal with and how to treat a banned and deleted character and which memories of the character continue to exist, if any.

## Rule 5: Job Whitelists

All roles, except for the passenger and the freelancer / contractor roles are whitelisted and require a job whitelist.

Players who seek employment on the station or with the Aurelian League, should generally join the server as normal and talk to Station Command, to get a job.

Freelancers and private Contractors work independently, minding their own business. No job whitelist is required. However, they still need a regular whitelist to play on the server. In addition, some jobs and activities might require a permit or license. Make sure to check Space Law to avoid legal issues. A lawyer can help you out with any paperwork you might need.

Removal from a job whitelist i.e a role ban means, that a player who is actively working this job, is effectively fired from their position. If they do not work the job, for which their whitelist has been removed, their employment and business activities remain unaffected.

Players, except for command staff, can only hold one job whitelist, for the job they are currently working.

If a players job whitelist is removed, this should be done in game and through RP, whereever possible. This allows the player to take legal actions, to defend themselves.

Should a role ban and thus the removal from a job whitelist occur as a result of an out of character or out of game incident, the player can appeal on Discord by opening a ticket.

Even if a role ban is issued due to out of game or out of character actions (for example metagaming, powergaming, etc.), the removal from the job should still be roleplayed out in game, so it makes sense and the player doesn't just disappear from their job. Be creative and work something out. If the role ban is temporary, the player could go on vaction. If it is permanent, maybe the player's in-game actions and behavior can be used as a reason, or some in-game event, such as a medical error during a surgery can be used.

Players who are permanently banned from the server or use their whitelist, automatically loose their job whitelist as well, since they are unable to join the server and play. Should the ban be lifted at a later time, the player should speak to the Head of Personnel to have their job and thus their role whitelist restored and work out any conditions, that may apply.

If a ban is temporary, the player can be considered, taking a course or training, being on vacation or maybe being interned in the infirmary for health or psycological issues for role-playing purposes.


## Rule 6: Listen to the Game Masters

Admins are called Game Masters here, in the Final Frontier. They are responsible for the smooth running of the server, host events, oversee the game and take actions, where required.

Their instructions are law and all players are required to follow them and listen to all our staff members.

If you feel a staff member has said or done something inappropriate or if you feel offended or have an issue with our staff, please open a ticket on Discord and let us know. DO NOT USE AHELP in such situations, as this can be seen by all staff members, including the person, you are reporting. Only by opening a ticket on Discord, it is assured, that your concern reaches the appropriate staff member for review.

Game Masters are open for ideas, concerns and questions. They are there to help you and make sure you have fun. Don't hesitate to contact them if you have questions, issues, or a good idea for an event.

## Rule 7: Character Names

All characters must have appropriate names, in accordance to their species lore and customs, unless there is a strong and valid RP reason, for them to not follow that rule (for example a moth, raised by humans, on earth or a human colony).

While players are allowed to create a character using their real name, the use of real names of celebrities, politicians, etc. is not allowed! Players can however create a character, which is a descendant of such a restricted person, if that person exists in their species law. That said, it is completely fine, to have a character, who is the descendant of a former president or governor or famous revolt leader and so on.

Offensice, racist or discriminating character names are strictly forbidden. Creating a character with such a name will result in an immediate ban and whitelist removal! If you are unsure whether a name is fine or not, ask on Discord or open an AHELP request. Rather be safe than sorry!

Game Masters and other staff members can rename characters, who do not meet naming conventions or use forbidden or inappropriate character names. Whenever possible, the GameMaster approaches the affected player, informs them about the issues and helps them to find an appropriate name, they like. Exceptions can be made for severe cases, where the player is not connected or unresponsive and immeidate action is required.

## Rule 8: Character Speech

All characters are required to use proper speech, when using verbal communication. Slangs, and talk, appropriate to the situation (such as gangster talk between criminals) is allowed. However, internet speech, leet talk, and internet acronyms such as LOL, ROFL, LMAO etc. are not allowed in verbal communication. They are however allowed in written communication, such as letters, faxes, emails, PDA chat, etc.

Offensive language may be allowed, depending on the situation and so are properly role-played insults. Using offensive language in OOC chat or IC, to discriminate or insult someone OOC, is strictly prohibited.

## Rule 9: Character Description

All player characters have a description field, they can use to describe physical attributes of their character, such as approximate size, skin color, scarfs, injuries, missing limbs, disabilities, etc.

Players are only allowed to provide such information in the info field, that is physically visible or can be otherwise discerned (slurred speech, hard hearing or deaf, etc). It is not allowed to put any kind of information here, that cannot be known by a player, without the player telling them and it cannot be used for secret messages, communication or any other means.

Every player character should have their description field filled out properly and with all relevant information. This is part of the character creation and vital for realistic RP.

Players violating this rule might be warned or banned from the server, depending on the severity of the infringement.

## Rule 10: Character Limit

Each player is allowed to have one character. This character needs to be well fleshed out and needs to have a character bio, if it wishes to be eligible for whitelist and whitelisted roles.

Additional characters can be made with admin approval, but characters can only be swapped between shifts. All additional characters need to be well fleshed out, need a proper character bio and need to undergo through interview and training, etc. to receive a job whitelist.

Characters are separate from one another. While they may be related to each other (family, husband, wife, etc.), it is not allowed to share confidential information between them, exchange items with each other or use one, to gain access to a restricted area or commit crimes with the other. This is considered metagaming and will result in a ban or warning and will also result in random deletion or removal of all but one characters.

## Rule 11: IC Relationships and Hostility

Players are allowed to play their characters in a way they seem fit. This includes being arrogant, uncooperative, rude or any other type of character, as long as this is played consistently and in a realistic way.

Relationships and ERP are allowed, as long they are played out in a realistic and serious way, that makes sense and enriches the role-play. However, all kind of ERP and romantic involvement or family role-play requires permission of all involved parties.

Mother / Father and Child Role-play is not allowed unless both characters are adults, and agree to that form of RP.

Pregnancy RP is not allowed, as their is no way, to role-play it out and play as a child or pregnant character.

RP of mental issues and illness is allowed, as long as it is done in a realistic way and with the required seriousness and delicacy of the matter. By no means, should mental issues or illnesses be played to discriminate or promote a certain cliché. Ahelp or open a ticket, if you have doubts or questions!

Since the server is persistent, relationships, hostility and reputation go a long way. You can not play as brother of another player and next turn magically are not brothers anymore, neither can you be rude this round and expect, that next round nobody remembers.

IC relationships and hostilities may under no circumstances have OOC consequences! Being rude, offensive or treat someone badly because of IC actions and hostility is not allowed and will result in a permanent ban!

## Rule 12: Role Limits and Restrictions

Except for law enforcement, all civilian and trainee rules are open for players without whitelist, so they can get into the game and start playing.

Regular positions require a whitelist. For more information on whitelist see the above rule on whitelisting.

Since the station is working with a fixed crew, each player can only play one character and hold one job. If you want to be a janitor, then you are a janitor. If you want to change jobs, you need to role-play the job change in a realistic way and need to follow the proper steps, for example obtaining permission from the Head of Personnel.

Command and in particular the HoP and the Captain can invite a player for a certain job or offer promotion. A technically skilled janitor could hence been asked by the Chief Engineer, if they want to become an engineer. In the case of civilians, only HoP and Department Head approval is required. In case of NT personnel, the current Department Head of the character must also approve transfer.

If you wish to change professional jobs, for example from Science to Medical, you need approval from both department heads and the Head of Personnel.

Players can be temporarily transferred to a different department or assigned to a particular job, if there is an emergency or the situation otherwise requires so and the character has the required skills to perform that task or assignment.

Temporary reassignments and transfers can be done by command, against the characters will, if this is required to safe the station, prevent bodily harm or property damage or if a situation otherwise requires it. Such temporary assignments are temporary. Once the task has been completed or the situation requiring the transfer has been resolved, the player is to be reassigned to their original duties.

On player run ships and in player factions, it is up the faction leader and the players, how they organize. For example, players can vote on who does what, name a faction leader who makes the decisions, or are jack of all trades, where everybody works what is needed. However, realistic role-play is still required. Nobody can realistically be an expert in everything!

## Rule 13: Do your Job, Stay inside your Role

Your character is a living being with a specific tasks or rolls and skills needed to perform this job. So do your job. Don't try to do everything! You can't and it might be considered powergaming (see powergaming below).

Players are supposed to have the basic skills to do their assigned jobs. An engineer knows how to fix stuff, the doctor knows how to heal somebody etc. Additionally, players can specialize within their job. An engineer might specialize in atmospheric tech, a doctor might specialize in chemistry and a scientist might specify in genetics or robotics.

However, players generally should have no knowledge about other jobs or roles, unless their is a plausible way for them to have such skills and this is known to the crew and / or properly role-played. Even if you, as the player are a perfect chemist, if you play an engineer, you know engineering and don't have any chemistry knowledge, unless you have worked as a chemist before and changed jobs.

Exceptions to the above are made for common basic skills, that everybody could plausibly aquire. For example, it is expected, that NT crew member and even most civilians know how to do basic CPR, and how to use an emergency medpen, since they underwent a first aid course and everybody knows how to change a light bulb or use the janitor equipment for cleaning. However, the average player wouldn't know, which chemicals or medications to inject for treatment of specific diseases and damage, how to use cryo or cloning equipment, or how to set up solar panels or an AME, unless they have experience in that area and received some specific training.

## Rule 14: Rounds and Shifts

Rounds last between several weeks or months, up to a full year.

Technical problems and limitations, required server updates and patches or other circumstances may change this. During alpha and beta, shorter shift and round times are possible and likely to happen.

No emergency shuttle is being called automatically. It is up to the command crew, to decide if it is necessary to call the shuttle. However, the shuttle should only be called, if there is an emergency and if the station is lost. If it is possible, to fix the station, even if such fixes take many hours or days, the crew should not abandon the station but continue their shift.

It is not allowed to end the shift or call a shuttle to leave. The shift goes on, until the station is lost or admin permission is given to evacuate.

## Rule 15: Logging out and Cryoing

Cryobeds are disabled and have been removed from the map. Instead all players are assigned quarters, with beds, where they can retire and go to sleep, if they wish to log out.

No player should abandon a shift without permission and crew members should let their department head know they are leaving. Department Heads and command staff should not log out, without notifying the other command members and making sure their department is left with someone (temporarily) in charge.

The Captain and the Executive Officer should not log out without letting CentComm know and making sure, someone is left in command, with access to the bridge and the required consoles. This should ideally be the Station AI or a Department Head.

## Rule 16: Death and Incapacitation

Death is permanent, unless the character can be cloned or revived. So don't fall into chasms or get vaporized, without having a clone ready.

Players are required to report to the infirmary, to have their clone data stored for cloning. Since cloning is done with the latest data on file, players should update their clone data frequently, to make sure, they retain most of their knowledge.

If a player is cloned, they loose all knowledge they have obtained since their last clone update. So go and see medical frequently!

A player who is killed with no clone on file, and rotting or otherwise unable to be revived, is permanently killed! So be careful! Get your clone stored!

Players who are executed as a result of a punishment for a crime they committed, have all their clone data removed before execution and are not to be revived, meaning they are also permanently dead and loose their character. Keep it in mind, before committing capital crimes with death punishment!

There are in-game means, to deal with death, such as heritage, DNR and DNC (do not clone / do not revive) orders. This should be RP'd out in game, with the help of lawyers and is further described in Space Law.

## Rule 17: SSD and AFK Players

SSD players, are players who are logged out of the game and are no longer connected. They cannot RP and they cannot respond. They are simply not there.

Since players are not allowed to log out of the game outside their quarters, the most likely cause is, that the player's game has crashed or they had to leave due to unforeseen circumstances, without having time to go to retire to their quarters.

Players who find a character with SSD outside the living quarters, should call security and let them know about the situation and the location of the player. Security will deal with it and if the player doesn't return from SSD within a reasonable amount of time (five to 10 minutes), will bring them either to their quarters or to medical for treatment.

Players who are not security should avoid interacting with SSD players, such as moving them out of the way or stowing them into some quarters. It is the job of security! An exception is made, in order to move someone suffering from SSD out of immediate danger, or if movement is required, because they are blocking access to an important area and there is no time to wait for security.

Security may perform a search of SSD players, to make sure they hold no dangerous, illicit or otherwise critical items, that could pose a threat to the station, especially if they would fall into the wrong hands.

Any illegal items found during, may be confiscated. Equipment, that is property of NT, or NT department and pose a risk if they would fall into the wrong hands (example: insulated gloves, remotes, etc.), should be taken from the character and returned to the department, after the player has been stowed away properly.

Command staff should be returned to their quarters or a secure area, in the command section, if possible, to avoid any items and equipment being stolen from them. If that is not possible, the HoS should take away any items that pose a security risk and hand them to the HoP or Captain if possible. In case the SSD character is the Captain or HoP, with the other not being around, the HoS shall store such items and hand them over to the Captain or HoP as soon as possible! It is the responsibility of the HOS, to make sure, the equipment is safe.

Command staff is still responsible for their crew, even if they are suffering from SSD and are logged out. This means, that if an emergency arises they must be moved to safety and if the station is evacuated, they have to be moved onto the shuttle before departure.

Players are not allowed to be AFK for an extended period of time, while in the game. It is okay, to take a bio break or grab some coffee, but longer absence should be avoided, as AFK players, since they are connected, are required to respond to comms, report to their duties or react to an emergency. If you need to do something, go to your quarters, go to sleep, log out or close the game and come back when you are done!

## Rule 18: Station AI and Silicons

Playing Silicons and especially the Station AI requires special skills and for that reason these roles are whitelist only.

Station AI is a command position and has to be approved / appointed by CentComm.

Players, being the Station AI, are required to play realistically. While it is fine to role-play software issues and bugs, abusing the Station AI and its powers is not allowed.

Since silicons are not sentient, they cannot be bribed. Reprogramming is possible, but needs to be role-played properly, especially in case of the Station AI.

Silicons and cyborgs are required to follow their laws, unless there is a realistic and plausible reason not to do so (system errors, being hacked or hijacked, etc.). This has to be role-played properly and in a realistic way (acting weird, have malfunctions, viruses, etc.).

Silicons cannot change their own laws or routines and are required to follow orders of their owners or authorized personnel, unless there is a plausible reason not to do so. Be creative if you want to do something, you shouldn't, so that everybody can enjoy the RP.

##Rule 19: Powergaming and Metagaming

Powergaming is the use of superpowers or playing a character in an unrealistic and overly powerful way, or using exploits, even if the game mechanics allow to do so. For example, if one player confronts five hostiles all alone, rushing into combat, killing them all, then healing their wounds, fixing all the damage and act like a hero, it is considered powergaming. Make sure you role-play properly, act reasonably and within your skills and abilities!

Metagaming is the usage of out of character information, out of game information or information from other characters, obtained by out of game means, to gain an advantage or act upon them in game. If you see someone on Twitch sneaking onto the station to steal something, and you use this information, to stop them, you are metagaming.

Both metagaming and powergaming ruin the role-play experience of everybody but yourself. Don't do it, or you might be warned or banned.

## Rule 20: Mutiny and Hijacking

Mutinies, hijacking and kidnapping and other crimes are allowed, as long as it is role-played properly.

Be aware though, that if you are caught, you are being punished and if you committed a capital crime, you are likely going to spend the rest of your life in jail or you are being executed. So be prepared to face the consequences.

## Rule 21: Safe Zones

Safe zones are meant to protect offline, SSD and AFK players.

The game mechanics do not allow locking personal quarters (public / civilian airlocks) and there is no way to assign individual access to doors. However, it is common sense, that such rooms would be locked in real life, allowing access only to the inhabitant of the room, security and command staff. As such, personal quarters are considered a safe zone for players who are logged out, AFK or suffering from SSD.

Players have no access to other players quarters, unless they are being invited, get a key card (role-play), or belong to a group of persons, with general access (security, command, CentComm, etc.). However, it is possible to role-play a break-in, hacking the door electronics or gain access through other means, such as breaking a window, etc. as long as it makes sense and is role-played properly. However, this is only allowed, if the player is online and active.

Characters logging out, suffering SSD or going AFK in their personal quarters, are protected, and it is not allowed to break in, or take any items from them, including their PDA, ID, Locker or Wardrobe items, etc.

Please note: Quarters which have their doors unpowered, due to a technical issue, such as APC failure, general power loss, energy emergencies, etc. are an exception!. They do not provide any protection for players, even if they are AFK or logged out! Wrongdoers and criminals can break in and abduct crew members or steal from them! It is the job of security, to make sure that during a power loss on the station, the quarters, as well as any other vital area of the station, are safe.

Should quarters be shared, access is assumed to be given to all crew members, who share the room. In this case, offline protection does not take effect and the sharing players can enter the room and commit crimes, even if the other players are offline. However, this must still be role-played properly and is also pretty obvious, and security will know right away, who has done it. So watch out!

## Rule 22: Streaming Policy

Streaming is welcome within the Final Frontier community, and streamers are permitted to broadcast content to a larger audience. However players and streamers alike are expected to exercise care within the in-game environment in a few ways.

Streamers are held to the same standard as all normal players, and are expected to follow all other rules and regulations listed. Streaming does not give special permission to break any outlined rules.

Players may not seek out streamers for the sole intent of interfering or hindering the stream, known as stream sniping. Attempts to seek out streamers to forcefully bait them into combat may also be considered stream sniping. Depending on the severity of the violation, admins may elect to bypass warning escalations and apply an appropriate ban.

Players may not use information gathered from streams in-character, and is considered to be meta-information. Acting upon information from a stream will result in disciplinary action. Likewise, streamers may not act upon information in-game that they have been provided from their chat.

Streamers are not required to AHELP beforehand, however it is highly recommended by staff. Ahelping with information of the expected duration of the stream can assist heavily in the quality of the stream, allowing admins to monitor for stream snipers, use of meta information, and potentially adding interest into the stream in the form of events if they are inclined.

## Rule 23: Warning and Punishment

Players found breaking the rules are subject to punishment and disciplinary actions.

Punishment is devided into in game and out of game punishment. These server rules cover only out of game punishment. In game punishment is covered by Space Law and other in-game regulations and standing orders.

Out of game punishment might involve or include in-game punishment. For example, a player gettnig a role ban for an out of game incident, will be fired from their job in-game, sine they cannot longer perform their duties.

Punishment includes: Verbal Warnings, Written Warnings / Admin Notes, Temporary Role Bans, Permanent Role Bans, Temporary Server Bans, Permanent Server Bans and Whitelist Removal.

Generally, punishment should increase gradually, from lowest to highest. However, depending on the severeness of the incident, staff may decide to skip one or several options. For example, a player found being involved in severe metagaming, might receive a temporary ban, without any prior warning, while a player hacking the server or exploiting game mechanics, is likely to be perma banned immediately.

It is the decision of staff, to decide which punishment to apply. Players feeling that they have been treated incorrectly, can appeal the punishment, opening a ticket on Discord.

If a player is banned, the banning staff member must inform the member about the ban and let them know, that they can appeal and how to do so.

## Rule 24: Appeals and Complaints

All players have the right to complain, if they feel, someone has insulted them or treated them wrongly.

If a player feels, that they have been victim of staff abuse, they are encouraged to report the staff member.

Players who have been banned or had their whitelist removed or their whitelist application rejected, may appeal the decision on Discord.

All appeals should be done on Discord, by opening a ticket. Appeals should never be done in public or whitelist chat, as forum threads or via DM or in-game!

Staff members deal with complaints of players, unless they involve a staff member. In this case, the Community Manager or the Project Lead will review the case. If the complaint is about the Community Manager, the Project Lead will handle it and if it is about the Project Lead, the second Project Lead (if there is one), handles the complaint. If there is no second Project Lead, the complaint should be handled by the Community Manager.

Staff members may not handle appeals of their own cases. Instead, the next higher instance (staff member >> senior staff >> community manager >> project lead) should handle the appeal.

Appeals are once and final, unless mentioned otherwise in the appeal. This means, that if your appeal as been denied, it is denied for good. Don't keep appealing. In many cases, the player is allowed to appeal again, after a certain amount of time has passed or after the player has met certain conditions. This will be communicated in the appeal response.

Note: This section only deals with out of character appeals. In-game appeals are covered by Space Law and usually involve a court case and trial.
</Document>
